<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: goodbye | Shit Gary Says]]></title>
  <link href="http://garylarizza.com/blog/categories/goodbye/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://garylarizza.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-25T16:13:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://garylarizza.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gary larizza]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some other beginning's end]]></title>
    <link href="http://garylarizza.com/blog/2017/08/25/some-other-beginnings-end/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-25T15:35:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://garylarizza.com/blog/2017/08/25/some-other-beginnings-end</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first day at Puppet, James Turnbull sat me down next to Jeff McCune and
waited for things to happen. That was partly because he knew that Jeff&rsquo;s
attention to detail would offset my attention to <code>git commit -a -m 'blkajdfs'</code>,
and partly because there were about 30 of us in the office and we all had shit
to do. Jeff was kinda working on an MCollective module back then, and I had
been using it pretty heavily at the school, so I decided to jump right in and
start hacking it up. To make a long story short, that experience working on the
MCollective module resulted in:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://projects.puppetlabs.com/issues/8040">Ticket number 8040 on class containment being filed by Jeff</a> (AKA &ldquo;How the Anchor pattern was born&rdquo;)</li>
<li>An understanding in how to use git as something more than just glorified rsync</li>
<li>An &ldquo;Odd Couple&rdquo; friendship with a guy who has &ldquo;right foot&rdquo; and &ldquo;left foot&rdquo; socks</li>
</ol>


<p>Over the next 4 years I would keep going back to Jeff whenever something new
puzzled me, and he would keep giving me pointers that directed me down the
right path.  I <a href="http://bit.ly/pryisawesome">learned about Pry</a> from Jeff when
I was working on the <code>directoryservice</code> provider and couldn&rsquo;t figure out why my
variables had no value, my understanding on the principles of unit testing came
from completely screwing up spec tests, and my blog posts on type/provider
development never would have happened if I didn&rsquo;t make all those mistakes and
have someone help me learn from them.  So when I hit that point at Puppet where
I began thinking about moving on to &ldquo;the next big thing,&rdquo; Jeff was a natural
choice.</p>

<p>With that in mind, I&rsquo;m happy to announce that as of September 7th, 2017 I&rsquo;ll be
joining Jeff at <a href="openinfrastructure.co">openinfrastructure.co</a> where we&rsquo;ll be
available to consult on everything from DevOps practices, Puppet
deployments/module development/etc, and &ldquo;how you turn ordinary socks into
&lsquo;right foot socks&rsquo; and &lsquo;left foot socks.&rsquo;&rdquo; (I&rsquo;m MOSTLY kidding on the last bit,
but that&rsquo;s not my area of expertise, soooo&hellip;..)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been 6.5 years of consulting with Puppet Inc. and I&rsquo;m not planning on
stopping anytime soon. I&rsquo;m grateful for all the opportunities and experiences
that have come my way, and I&rsquo;m looking forward to going back to a smaller work
environment and more freedom to choose those opportunities! If you have one of
those opportunities and are looking for someone to help you out,
please look us up at
<a href="http://www.openinfrastructure.co">http://www.openinfrastructure.co</a> and let us
know about it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
